<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Copy of a letter to a countrey collonel, or, A serious dissuasive from joyning with those officers now in rebellion against the Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259524</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34494)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 177:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Copy of a letter to a countrey collonel, or, A serious dissuasive from joyning with those officers now in rebellion against the Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Warning against support of army groups defecting to the royalist cause; contains references to Booth's uprising.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57795:1"/>
            <head>The Copy of a LETTER To a Countrey Collonel, OR, A ſerious Diſſuaſive from joyning with thoſe Officers now in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Par novum fortuna videt concurrere, bellum</l>
                  <l>Atque virum —</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am informed that you are invited again into armes. Before you do it I deſire you to look round about you; and conſider well <hi>The Call, The Cauſe, The Company</hi> you are to engage with, and the <hi>Enemies</hi> you are to oppoſe. For if it be true, that war is never juſt but when 'tis neceſſary (&amp; which is never ſo but when there is no other remedy,) That armes are never warrantable but when they are taken up for preventing or repelling ruining miſchiefs, evils of the firſt magnitude; and for preſerving, recovering or acquiring ſuch good things, as every eye may ſee, and every tongue will confeſſe are eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to the being, or univerſally deſirable to the better being of a people, or cauſe concerned therein; and laſtly, That the authority which calls to armes, and can only make killing no murder, and triumphing no treaſon, muſt be unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable. A man had need of more then good company and a good perſwaſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his friends and enemies reſpectively, to induce him to this extreme and worſt of remedies. But before I come to ſearch the Cauſe, or diſpute the Call; which ſtands firſt (in order of nature) to be conſidered: let me intreat you to look well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the quality of your company; becauſe I fear your greateſt temptation lyes on that hand. I confeſſe, ſome years ſince there was an Army, and there were Officers that did
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57795:2"/>worthily in <hi>Ephratah,</hi> and were famous in <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> But ſure you are much miſtaken, if you think this, that Army &amp; theſe thoſe Officers who fought ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for our liberties as men &amp; Chriſtians, who jeoparded their lives ſo often, ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably, and (through grace) ſo ſucceſſefully in the high places of the field in all the three Nations, againſt a violent and vindictive King, and his ſon (in nothing unlike his father, but that he is more vicious.) This certainly is not that Army, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe are not thoſe Officers which thought thoſe Members onely worthy to ſit as the Leg ſtators of three Nations, by whoſe counſels chiefly they had conquer'd two, and reſcued the third out of the pawes of the Lyon; and when they had done it, wanted not cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to ſit upon him in judgement, and cut off his head: a terrible and eternall example to all that ſhould thereafter uſurpe or abuſe a power over a generous and free-born people.</p>
            <p>But indeed this is that Army, or very like it, and theſe thoſe Officers, who, when they had done thoſe great things under the Parliaments authority and conduct, had been duly paid by them as the beſt of ſervants, owned by them as brethren, tendred and provided for as children, honoured and rewarded as the very ſaviours of their country, deſerted their maſters, their brethren, their fathers, and their patrons; and layd their conquering weapons at the foot of their fellow ſervant, planting the laurel (I had almoſt ſaid the crown, but in that I had ſaid leſſe) upon his temples, who poſſibly if he had been born to it, or had never taken it, might have been thought worthy of one: but having ſo taken it by diſeaſing his Maſters, and putting a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon that authority which he owned and ſerved while he commanded their forces, got nothing thereby more then a ſad and deplorable reproach upon religion, unparalell'd loſſes and oppreſſions on the people, a general fruſtration of all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, wounds, and a laſting diſhonour upon his name, a ſpirit ſo broken by unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous infidelity, and an heart and life ſo conſtantly aſſaulted with fears and terrours, that he needed not (amongſt men) any greater puniſhment then a longer time of hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſuffering thoſe ſplendid horrors.</p>
            <p>At his end, leaving the Nation ready to expire with him under the weight of it's own confuſions and an unſupportable debt, a diſhonourable peace, and a war not more improvident then unprofitable.</p>
            <p>Theſe Officers, <hi>Sir,</hi> are ſomething like thoſe who gave their ſingle perſon a lowder negative then ever any King of <hi>England</hi> was entituled or pretended to; and a larger purſe then any Sovereign before either had or needed: and which was worſt, therein exempted him from the fear of ever needing any Parliaments (if he could have kept his ambition within any bounds) and the people from the hopes of receiving any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by them. And 'tis moſt like, ſo like that Army as if it were the very ſame, which very lately interrupted that Parliament, whom they had not ſix months before owned (with ſelf-ſhame and repentance for their former injurious actings againſt them) the only lawfull authority of the Nation: and that at a time when they were induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſtudying to ſettle the government disjoyned by former uſurpations, and not yet (as it ſeems) ſettled to general ſatisfacton; reſupplying their treaſuries miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably exhauſted by miſmanagements of the late governments, with as little charge or grievance as might be to the people (and ſolely, if poſſibly, out of the Eſtates of Sir
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57795:3"/>
               <hi>George Booth</hi> and other traitors and Apoſtates) for the pay of the Army; and that moſt juſt, but almoſt forgotten debt of the Publick faith, and not to be infinite, when they were providing againſt that dangerous combination of thoſe two great and Malignant conſtellations of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> united (as is credibly reported and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally believed) to our ruine in the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Kings reſtitution; and when malice it ſelf being judge, they were not doing any thing that had the leaſt tendency to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe or weaken that good and righteous cauſe they and the Army had been ſo long engaged in.</p>
            <p>This, <hi>Sir,</hi> is the company that you are to keep, thoſe are the men you are to be allied to in bloud. My ſoul enter not thou into their ſecret, for their wrath is cruel. But you will ſay (or they no doubt will ſay) Is there not a Cauſe, and ſure there had need be an hugely great one for ſuch furious and deſtructive proceedings: a Cauſe-deſtroying Cauſe, or a complication of cauſes and miſchiefs intollerable, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe incurable for ſuch an over-turning violence.</p>
            <p>Why, read their own Declaration, weigh the matters therein alledged, well, take them all for granted, and then give righteous judgement; and ſay, or let themſelves when they are themſelves, ſay if they have a righteous cauſe for ſuch unrighteous actings. In the year 1648, they held forth that the greater number of Members in Parliament were apoſtatized and had made defection to the King's intereſt after they had declared they would make no more addreſſes to him; having plainly diſcovered that in the preſervation of his perſon and authority, they could not preſerve our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and liberty. And therefore they ſecluded them from their ſhare of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: is there any thing that has the reſemblance to that ſo much as charg'd upon the Parliament now? or can they inſtance in any one debate, vote, or reſolution which did in the leaſt threaten that <hi>Good old Cauſe.</hi> Themſelves (as little ingenuous as they are) and as little our friends, do not pretend it: and, which could onely have juſtified their putting a period (as much as in them is) not onely to all the preſent, viſible, lawfull authority of the nation, but deſtroying the very root of all civil power, and from whence onely future repreſentatives (if ever they intend us any) can be regularly derived, and ſafely provided for. But we will not ſearch for what we are ſure not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o find a juſt, full and competent cauſe. Themſelves have ſtated it upon the Parliaments Votes for taking away ſome Officers commiſſions, and the ruine (as they imply) of their families thereby; a mighty cauſe ſure, and very honourably held forth by them who made no conſcience to deſigne (and which they now endeavour to carry on) the ruine or hazard of three Nations, rather then ſuffer an eclipſe in the power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of nine boyſterous gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lemen, who yet are very far from being ruined by this deſerved reducement; having ſuch eſtates, for which not long ſince ſome of them deemed themſelves fit to ſit in an houſe of Peers, who before the wars were ſcarcely qualified for an election into the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Little remembring, it ſeems, that to make them way; whole brigades, whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies who had born the firſt brunt and a great part of the heat of the war, held it their duty, at the Parliament's command to disband, and to be reduc'd not onely from your commands, but ſome of them that had been eminent in ſervice, to a morſel of bread and little leſſe then beggery.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57795:4"/>Whereas now if a cheap and unbloudy victory be not recompenc't not onely with pay, but titles and ſalaries to general Officers, and if marks of favour beſides titles &amp; ſalaries be not conferred upon thoſe that appeared forward in this late action, it muſt not be born no not in a Parliament, but ſtand as an unpardonable crime, and worthy to be puniſht with the loſſe of their authority: as if a 1000 <hi>l.</hi> to the Commander in chief of that Brigade, 500 <hi>l.</hi> beeween two Officers that ſeem to have ſignalized themſelves in that expedition, an 100 <hi>l.</hi> to the Captain that brought up the newes, and 3. hundred to that worthy Gentleman that kept the Cittadel till relief came to him, were not convenient gratuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es for a Commonwealth ſunk to ſo great a degree and almoſt extremity of want; by means of a Government themſelves had ſet up and aſſerted, which beſide the loſſe of many millions in ſhipps and trade, had involved the Nation in a debt of more then two — to the ſouldiery by ſea and land.</p>
            <p>And was it not a good mark of favour, to ingage the proceed of all Delinquents Eſtates new and old for the ſatisfaction of the ſouldiers whole arrears, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd from the time that they turn'd them out, and during the time they kept them out of the exerciſe of their lawfull authority: the Parliament (ſo indulgent were they to them that now requite them ſo ill) reſolving to pay them, if not for yet while they held the pikes at their breaſts, and choſe to own a ſingle perſon before and againſt a whole Nation, yea three Nations and their Repreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntatives: from which ſatisfaction they did not exempt any, even the moſt active of theſe Officers, the authors of all their wrong and the peoples miſeries: after which all reaſonable men will be to ſeek what favours and rewards can be proportionable to the unlimited opinion which theſe men hold of their own unmatchable deſervings.</p>
            <p>But by theſe things we begin to underſtand the meaning of that negative character that ſo often they ſtile themſelves by, &amp; boaſt themſelves in, as that they are no <hi>Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Army. It appears now (though not now firſt) that beſides their pay they muſt have honourable gratuities, and that themſelves muſt be the onely judges of what are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſo. 'Tis not enough that they were payed to a penny while they were faithfull and ſuffered the Parliament to ſit (and if they have wanted ſince, whom have they to blame but themſelves?) 'Tis not enough that their Commanders have been more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently and plentifully rewarded then any under Heaven for ſervices, wherein for the moſt part the private ſouldiers ſuffer moſt in life and limb, without any other conſideration then a little pillage and a letter of thanks ſcatterd amongſt them, but they muſt carve out their own gratuities propor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ionable to their avarice and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or elſe they are not pleas'd: and over and above all, muſt have alſo an indefei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zable eſtate of fee-ſimple in thoſe commands and offices, and hold no longer at will of their Maſters: a tenure which the beſt skill'd armies in the trade of war and the military Diſcipline never underſtood or pretended to in former times.</p>
            <p>And yet all this is not enough to compleat the meaning of <hi>Unmercenary,</hi> but they muſt thereby alſo be intitled to a ſhare in the Legiſlature, not as members, (ſome of them) of Parliament, but as the body of an army, by ſtating Propoſals which muſt not be deny'd, hardly debated or diſputed, nor without a high offence, delayd; or, which is more, to have a total negative upon all the authority of the Nation; or which is moſt, and moſt unſupportable) themſelves to poſſeſſe the Legiſlative power, and a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57795:5"/>right to make and make voyd, to repeal and inſtitute Lawes not onely martial but of a civil nature alſo, which none but the people or their deputies can without much ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance or ignorance pretend unto, and which no people ever ſuffered but ſuch as could not help it, were borne under it, or cheated, or conquered to it.</p>
            <p>But what talk we of ſuch petty powers, ſuch low preheminences, ſuch inferior pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of nulling, repealing or making Lawes, nay Governments for a people whom they dare not ſay they have conquered: they claim ſomething higher and more abſolute, <hi>non eſt mortale quod optant:</hi> 'tis not enough to be above all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led man, but they muſt judge and puniſh as God himſelf does; as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they know the meaning of the Parliament; and by a God-like authority they will puniſh the iniquity of their intentions though never diſcovered, or drawn forth into ouert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act; for do not they and their paraſites charge, that the Parliament meant to bring in the King, to acquit <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> George Booth</hi> who rebell'd for him, and in order thereunto to diſcompoſe and alter the conſtitution of the Army, (which ſurely they needed not to have done upon that occaſion) moſt of them being but too well acquainted with the trade of King-making, or which is all one, of ſetting up ſingle perſons above and in place of Kings. But certainly of all calumnies in the world, this though ſuggeſted with never ſo much impudence can never ſtick, for let the Army be (if they will) more and wiſer then men; is the Parliament leſſe or worſe then beaſts? have they not by all their experience and that ſtock of reaſon thats left them? yet learnt the dictates of nature and the princples of ſelf-preſervation? can they be ſuppoſed willing to truſt a King whoſe father they beheaded, and having deſtroyed ſo many Cavaliers, at laſt prove <hi>felones de ſe,</hi> and truſt themſelves and their ſecurity upon the crazy faith of thoſe not yet reconciled enemies, more enraged and exaſperated by ſo many defeats and ruines.</p>
            <p>But there are ſome (who are pleas'd to think more charitably of the Parliament) as to the care of our civil liberties, who will yet ſuſpect them of a rigid Presbyterian ſpirit gendring to perſecution in matters of conſcience, to all ſuch we ſubmit to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration the votes of the Committee for government ſo often alledged by others, and made publick in many papers, in which was granted more then the Army ſaw reaſon to ask in their Propoſals (but perhaps they meant more, and 'tis the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments crime that they were not Gods too, and could not be able to know the ſecret receſſes of their hearts and their thoughts afar off: was there not then yielded at leaſt as much as any ſober Chriſtian can wiſh or bear, that owns a God in Chriſt: That there is a pattern of wholeſome words, and ſome clear fundamental truths to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for; that there are ſome damnable hereſies and doctrines of devils to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and that would not themſelves live as without God in the world, or have the Magiſtrates while he gives equal protection to all Chriſtians, himſelf be none, or no more then an heathen.</p>
            <p>You ſee then the quarrell and the cauſe you are to fight for, which principally is the diſcharging of nine officers from their commands who had (ſome of them) as <hi>nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> removed nine ſcore guilty of no other crime then what themſelves had not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been only deeplyer dyed in; and for this you are to fight againſt the Parliament and the aſſertors of their authority, &amp; becauſe they were ſo bold as to refuſe their chief
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57795:6"/>Commander a Commiſſion illimited in power and time, and ſo good husbands for a poor beggarly Commonwealth as to deny the unneceſſary chargeable and dangerous qualityes of move generall Officers in a time of peace, and after they had ſuppreſs't a dangerous inſurrection without them, and laſtly becauſe they preſumed to be ſo wiſe as not to remit the <hi>removing</hi> of officers to the pleaſure of a <hi>Councell of war.</hi> Which they ſaw not long before had diſcharged Col. Okey, Alured, and other faithfull Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for oppoſing, that which themſelves ſhortly after pretended to repent of, nor to truſt the <hi>ſupplying</hi> of officers to thoſe <hi>nominators</hi> who were ſo late ſo imprudent, or ſo unhappy as to preſent to the Parliament, ſuch as ſome of theſe nine were, and now more fully diſcover themſelves to be. By all which propoſitions 'tis plain they deſigned to make their Army a new modell with a witneſs, an in tire ſelf ſubſiſting body perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant of the civill and Soveraigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, the only repreſentative of the only good people of the refined intereſt: unaccountable for any of their actions, but qualified to call all others to account, wanting nothing of omnipotency, but this, that though they can doe all things elſe, they cannot make the people believe them juſt and honeſt. And no wonder if upon this principle they were angry at the Parliament for giving and at themſelves for taking commiſſions from them whom they reſolved to obey no further or longer then themſelves ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p>Things ſtanding on theſe terms, can your heart endure, or will your hands be ſtrong to fight Generall Monck on ſuch a quarrell, when he ſhall advance to reſtore ſuch a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to the juſt exerciſe of their power, which they have improved hitherto with ſo much reaſon and reſolution to publick advantage, and is he become your enemy for telling you the truth and ſtanding for the right and juſtice of their cauſe. O tell it not in <hi>Gath</hi> leaſt the uncircumciſed rejoice, nor in <hi>Iudah</hi> leaſt our beſt friends be forc't to ſay this Northern Star outſhines the brighteſt Southern worthyes, &amp; though many of them have done worthily this one excells them all. I know other cauſes are alledged towards the juſtifying this tranſaction of the Army, which are rather occaſions then cauſes, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents then occaſions, as namely the haſty paſſing of ſome acts which at another ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would have had a maturer and more deliberate conſideration. But 'tis not well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that they had an Army hanging over their heads ready to turn them out of doors, and ſure they had need make haſt who muſt run the gandelope through an Army: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that by thoſe ſuddain votes they vacuated nothing, but was void in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery making, as done without a due legiſlative authority, &amp; which if not (in one prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> act) made void muſt have given the ſingle perſon a plauſible pretence to return upon us with 1300000 l. by the year and an Army to ſupport him. If thereby the deſerving miniſtry that were plac't in delinquents livings during their interruption were in danger to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, providence and the carefull ſedulity of the Parliaments Committee has made even ſince their diſturbance, and yet regularly ſo good a proviſion, that no worthy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter will have cauſe to complain of the Parliaments over haſty reſolutions. I wiſh their Tythes and maintenance be not more endangered by the Army then their pulpits by the Parliament, and yet thats not all their defence. They declared and enacted that nothing done in the time of their interruption ſhould be deemed lawfull or binding, but was it not with this ſalvo, unleſſe it had been or ſhould be enacted &amp; confirmed by them. And now I pray who hindred the Parliament from ſitting to enact and confirm
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57795:7"/>whatever of thoſe lawes or ordinances ſhould be found of advantage, and for the reall good of the people. If they had paſt ſuch an Act the 6. of May next, things in <hi>fumo jure,</hi> it muſt have been juſt, it would hardly have paſt for prudent or ſafe, but to do it when in their own both right and expectation they were to have ſate 6. moneths longer where was the danger, and therefore I know no fault it has: but that it was altogether contrary (as their declaration ſpeaks) to what was deſired in the third propoſall of the Petition and Addreſſe of the 12. of May: a ſoare crime not to underſtand the pleaſure of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which yet it's hoped the nation may forgive though the Army doe not.</p>
            <p>Howſoever ſure enough they will thank the Parliament for the other half of that Act, prohibiting the leavies of any money, otherwiſe then by authority of Parliament, by which it will be in their power to ſave their purſes, if they have as much courage as cauſe till they be opened by their own conſent in themſelves or their deputies.</p>
            <p>But woe is me I had forgot that which was indeed a cauſe for this action, and a very important one; the Parliaments Act of indemnity was too narrow, the plaiſter would not reach that ſoare place, but that Lambert is ſtill in danger of refunding the profits of the Aul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age, and the thouſands which were diſcharged by privy ſeals of money due upon a ſecond moity, and others for their Salaries as Treaſurers and Councellors, all which they acquired by ſetting up &amp; ſtanding by an unlawfull power, when as the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Commonwealths men were ſo eaſy as to ſerve 4. years and upwards that intereſt gratis, and now again upon their return returned into the ſame practiſe with the ſame principles, but I confeſſe they that hazard their cauſe and their conſcience had need have their penny for their penny worth. And now let themſelves ſay whither from this time forward they did not watch all occaſion to deſtroy the Parliament. One word more and then I have done, tell me how ſhall the Regiments you are to raiſe or call to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether be provided: Muſt you not by the Armies authority, or will you by your own (which is as good) leavy money upon the Countrey for their ſubſiſtance: If ſo, do but conſider, if ever England ſee a lawfull power again, whither they can aſſert their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and ſecure their ſitting, if they doe not ſeverely execute the penalties of thoſe lawes both old and new which call it treaſon to tax the people, and take their money without common conſent in Parliament, or if you deſigne free quartet think well of it, whither S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Bricies night may not be acted over again, or which is more Chriſtian and more adviſeable, the people may not ſee reaſon in their own defence even without the help of a Parliament to diſarm and reduce ſuch inſolent Lurdans, who ſhall ſo eat up the people like bread without a lawfull authority, and drink the ſweat of their browes without remorſe, not ſatisfied till by fleecing the poore Commons they ſeat themſelves again as Lords on wolſacks, and there with a more then Popelike arrogance pretend to 3 ſwords, military, civill, and ſpirituall, as the peoples Soveraigns, and yet contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them for pay as the meaneſt of ſervants: who while they deny Miniſters tythes and a forced maintenance, continue to enforce their own pay till they leave us not a ninth, who by a more Magiſteriall then cunning Chymiſtry are drawing all the wealth and power of the Nation into a refined intereſt, whereof themſelves muſt be the only judges and members, leaſt when they come again into the Peers Houſe, or which is the ſame the San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n, or Senate, it ſhould be again objected to them that their intereſt in the Nation is not conſiderable, becauſe their eſtates are not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57795:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Yet, in all this that I ſay, I would not be underſtood to ſpeak againſt the Army in its general and aggregate body, I doe in part mean the generall councell of Officers as now conſtituted and diſtempered, or I mean thoſe Officers that principally head this rebellion againſt the Parliament: nay perhaps I mean principally if not Solely, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Lambert the head and great engine of this great defection. I know an Army is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, I judge well of many in this, thoſe who have refuſed Commiſſions from this new ſelf created authority, and many others. And am not without an hopefull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion that of thoſe who are now marcht Northward, many doe go, with that mind that when they are come where they may doe it, with effect and advantage, they will deliver up their moſt obſtinate Officers to him who knows how to obey the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, fight Rebells, and maintain a good cauſe with an honeſt ſincerity and ſutable courage.</p>
            <p>To conclude I ſhould ſpeak ſomething of your call, but (upon due ſearch,) I find you have none, unleſſe you reckon that for one which you find in the firſt of the Proverbs, 10.11.12.13.14.15.16. verſes, which ſpeaks thus, (viz.) 10. <hi>My Son, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not,</hi> 11. <hi>If they ſay, come with us, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cauſe,</hi> 12. <hi>Let us ſwallow you up alive as the grave, and whole, as thoſe that goe down into the pit,</hi> 13. <hi>We ſhall find all precious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoil,</hi> 14. <hi>caſt in thy lot among us, let us all have one purſe,</hi> 15. <hi>My Son, walk not thou in the way with them; refraine thy foot from their path,</hi> 16. <hi>For their feet run to evill, and make haſt to ſhed blood,</hi> and if you think fit to anſwer ſuch a call upon your perill be it, I have juſtified my friendſhip, and delivered my ſoul by this to you. But take heed, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery overtake you not as an armed man and the juſtice of God number you amongſt the workers of iniquity, to which he deprecates in your behalf, who is;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
